<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A forme of preparation to the Lordes Supper meete for all such as minde with fruite and comfort to communicate in the same / written by T.W.</title>
            <author>T. W. (Thomas Wilcox), 1549?-1608.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1587</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15337</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25622.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2973</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">29616460</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 29616460</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28033</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15337)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28033)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1860:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A forme of preparation to the Lordes Supper meete for all such as minde with fruite and comfort to communicate in the same / written by T.W.</title>
                  <author>T. W. (Thomas Wilcox), 1549?-1608.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[87] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Waldegraue for Thomas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1587]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title enclosed in ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Imprint date suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: []⁴ A-E⁸.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catechisms, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:28033:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28033:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A <hi>Forme of preparation</hi> to the Lordes Supper, meete <hi>for all ſuch as minde with fruite</hi> and comfort to <hi>commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate in the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by T. W.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. COR. 13.5.6.</bibl>
               <p>¶Prooue your ſelues whether ye are in the fayth: examine your ſelues; know ye not your owne ſelues, how that IESVS CHRIST is in you, except yee bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates? But I truſt that yee ſhall know, that vve are not reprobates.</p>
            </q>
            <p>AT LONDON; <hi>Printed by</hi> Robert Walde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue <hi>for Thomas Man.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:28033:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28033:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the people and inhabitants of</hi> B. and H. in the countie of Hertford, health in Chriſt Ieſus.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Rethren, our hearts deſire, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt requeſte to almightye God for you day and night is, that you and al yours, might be inlightned by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, in your inward man, with the ſound knowledge, ſteadfaſt faith, and holy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of his bleſſed trueth, for the good and comfortable directyng of you, in the daies of your pilgrymage heer, and that your bodies and ſoules may (when the troubleſome time of the race that is ſet you, to runue in this life is expired) bee eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſaued, in that great and laſt day of the Lorde Ieſus. Of this moſt certaine truth, wee haue many good and ſufficient witneſſes (I hope) both within vs and without vs, at home and abroad: As firſt the eternall God, before whome though vvee haue walked, in great weakenes and wonderfull vvants, yet he knoweth that his glory, and your good, hath bene not onely the principall, but euen the alone mark we haue aimed at, in our publike places And if men may be admitted as teſtes in their own cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, not onely the vnfeigned affections of our harts to you-wards, but euen our ſound and ſincere acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſpiritually as in regard of our eccleſiaſtical mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, and that in all the partes of it, both praiers and preaching, ſhalbe proofes, pregnant and plain inough. True it is, that our hearts and mindes (as which are inward) are indeed known only to God, who alone is the ſearcher of the heart and reynes, and in whoſe ſight it ſhalbe ſufficient for vs to reſt as in this behalfe, in the perſwaſion of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.
<pb facs="tcp:28033:3"/> But for our outward dealinges and beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour that way, we are willingly content, to referre and ſubmit both it and our ſelues, not onely to the generall teſtimony, of all and euery one of you, but if any amongeſt you, bee leſſe zealous and forward in the goſpell then vvere to be wiſhed, we will thus farre offer our ſelues euen by your ſentences to bee tried, whether we haue dealt deceitfully vvith the worde, chopping and chaunging the ſame at oure pleaſures, yea or no, or haue bene vnmindefull of you, in our pore prayers, and faint requeſts though they be. To ſeeke letters of credit from abroad els where, when you your ſelues will not, vvith your hands alone, but with your hearts alſo yeeld vs (as we hope) &amp; that without feare, &amp; flattery, our iuſt commendation, may ſeeme ſuperfluous, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſith we ſtand not vpon them that are vvithout, further than as we may, (keeping our ſelues in the compaſſe of an ordinary and ſettled vocation) doe them what good we can in Chriſt. And yet (to the praiſe of God be it written and ſpoken) vvee may haue in that reſpect, the moſt graue and aſſured te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, not onely of godly and good men of our place, miniſters of the worde vve meane about vs, (vvhich ſheweth that wee haue not vvalked by our ſelues, as the manner of ſome is, in a proud and a contemptuous manner, and yet without cauſe the Lord knoweth, refuſing the company and confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of their brethren) but alſo if need be, of great numbers of ſuch, as be ſoundly lincked vnto vs, in the vnfeigned loue, ſincere knowledge, and holye profeſſion of Gods eternal truth: who though they cannot in euery particular yeeld teſtimony of vs, as you your ſelues, yet hauing in ſom meaſure ben
<pb facs="tcp:28033:3"/> faithful beholders of the holy conuerſation, and at ſundry times attentiue, and fruitfull hearers of the ſound doctrine that God hath enabled vs, both to performe and deliuer, cannot but iuſtifie vs, yea, ſure we are in both reſpects wil iuſtifie vs, and that to the comfort of our own conſciences, and to the ſtopping of the mouthes of the vvicked, alſo what vvee haue done priuatly to procure your good, it vvere better you your ſelues ſhoulde faithfullie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, and our chriſtian conferences had vvith you and yours, (ſpecially before the adminiſtration and participation of the Lordes Supper) trulye ſpeake, than vve, for our ſelues this we can proteſt, in truth and ſinceritie before God and man, that our care and toyle that vvay was not ſmall. VVhat fruite it brought forth, vvould to God that your workes of pietie tovvards his maieſty, and of charitie towards all men, might as effectually declare, as your ovvne words haue plainely vvitneſſed, many of you ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing conſtantlye aduouched to your ſelues and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that you haue bene by the ſame, not onelye vvell fitted for that holye action, but inſtructed for time to come, and comforted againſt the dayes of your diſtreſſes, yea ſom of you hauing further affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med (whether rightly yea or no looke yee to that) that that in diuers reſpects hath bene as profitable vnto you, as the word of vvholſome doctrine, and ſpirituall comfort, that God hath inabled vs in ſom meaſure publikely to deliuer amongſt you. In the ordinary exerciſes of our families, vve haue ſeldom ceaſed to offer vp holy ſacrifices to the Lord, as on your hehalfe. And this we haue done, without par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality and reſpect of perſons, though ſundry of you haue giuen fearfull occaſions to cauſe vs to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb facs="tcp:28033:4"/> the performance of this moſt neceſſary duty: vve yet notvvithſtanding morning and euening, bovving our knees, &amp; holding vp our hands to God the father of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt in our poore manner, praying him for you, that of his infinite goodnes it vvould pleaſe him, euen for his deare ſonnes ſake to pardon all our ſinnes, that ſo in the forgiuenes of them, a way might be made vnto his mercies, and the ſame amongſt many other means manifeſted in this, that our pore paines in preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing were not loſt, neither the time that your ſelues ſpent in hearing periſh, and ſo the vvorde become thorow negligence, carleſnes, or contempt of your hearts, and a ſecret iudgement of God againſt you for the ſame, the ſword of death vnto your ſoules. Neither do vvee now write this, as in the vaunting and glorious ſpirite of proud hearts before God &amp; men (for we haue, and ſhall alwaies haue within vs from our ſelues, as in reſpect of our greeuous ſinnes &amp; great inſufficiencye and without vs from you, as in regard of your coldnes &amp; careleſnes, matter ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to humble vs, and caſt vs down continualy) or as vnkindly to vpbraid you in any reſpect, vvith the chriſtian care we haue had for you, &amp; the great good that we haue ment to do to you (though yet we muſt freely confeſſe it in that behalfe, vvee vvill not vvillingly ſuffer our ſelues to bee ſpoiled of our iuſt ioy in that behalf) but to the end that we might yet at the length earneſtlye ſtirre you vp in ſome deepe conſideration, ſight &amp; feeling, of our vnfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned goodwils towardes you in Chriſt, not ſo much to ſhew your ſelues chriſtianly kinde and ſoundlie louing vnto vs (though yet we cannot but ſay that the very beholding of it, if vvee might once ſee it,
<pb facs="tcp:28033:4"/> would yeeld marueilous ioy &amp; comfort to our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy hearts) but firſt dutifull to the Lord, that euerye manner of vvay, in his rich liberality offereth you ſo infinit mercies, and aftervvards careful for your ſelues, not for the things of this world (for a laſſe vvee knowe by a lamentable experience, that you vvade to farre, and vvalk to much vp and down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe craggy and barren rocks of carke &amp; care) but for ſpirituall and heauenly graces, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for the ſauing of your ſoules, in that great and laſt day of the Lord Ieſus, for the better acompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vvhereof, vvee come yet again vnto you, and make offer of an other ſure token of vnfeigned af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: wee vvill not ſay the laſt teſtimony of our loue tovvards you (for vve hope that ſhall alwaies indure in the Lord, howſoeuer vve may be ſundred from you by bodily preſence) but in truth the laſt triall that vve mind to make of you, as in reſpecte of your ſteadfaſt faith to God, vnfeigned loue to men, and holy obedience to the Lords whole truth and euery part thereof, vvherein if by your ovvne good inclination, and the forvvardnes likevviſe of thoſe of your families, as vviues, children, ſeruants, &amp;c. (for all your good, yong and old, one vvith an other, haue we penned and pricked this ſhort trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe follovving) you vvill make glad our ſpirits and crovvn your ſelues with honor and immortality in the ſight of God &amp; men, committing to your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, for the increaſe of your knowledge, &amp; put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in practiſe for the ſtrengthening of your faith theſe good things that haue bene drawen for you, and are novv dedicated vnto you, vve ſhall humbly vpon the knees of our harts, thank the eternal ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, for ſuffering that gracious vvorke in you, and
<pb facs="tcp:28033:5"/> as his pore and vnworthy ſeruants, by continuance of our ſmall traueiles, do vvhat we can euen to the vttermoſt for your grovvth, increaſe, &amp; holding on vnto the end, in all goodnes &amp; truth for euermore. But if notvvithſtanding this, and other religious meanes before ſpecified, reuerently performed for your good, as on our behalfe you vvill remaine as you haue done, in your old ſinnes, of pride, vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalnes, couetouſnes, careleſnes, hipocriſie, hatred hardnes of heart, and many other ſuch like, we may (as vve ſhall haue iuſt cauſe) mourn all day long as the turtle, in that heauy iudgement of God againſt you, and vpon our labours alſo among you how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit vve ſhall reſt in the perſvvaſion and peace of a good conſcience before God, that vvee haue vſed tovvards you (as our weaknes vvould ſuffer vs) ſuch good helps and aids, as the Lord hath bene pleaſed to beſtow vpon vs, and to put into our minds and mouthes to profite you vvithall, and to build you vp into a holy temple for the lord, that ye might be a people zealouſlye giuen, and prepared for euerye good vvork. God the only both ſearcher &amp; ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the heart and reynes, vouchſafe for Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſake, the very meane and matter of all his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies tovvards vs, to make ſtreight your declining ſteps, leſt that which is halting be vtterly turned out of the vvay to ſoften your ſtony, yea, flinty harts, leſt thorow hardnes in your invvard parts, you ſtop the courſe of Gods grace, and the loue of his ſaints tovvards you: and ſo powerfully and vnfeignedly to conuert you vnto himſelfe, that you maye ſerue as precious veſſels for honorable vſes in his houſe which is his church, for euer &amp; euer: So be it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your louing brethren alwaies in Chriſt, and painefull Paſtors in the ſeruice of the word. T.VV. R.O.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:28033:5"/>
            <head>¶ LORD IESVS BEGIN and make an end.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>O you minde, when the time and order of oure Churche ſhall require, to celebrate the Lords ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, to communicate with the reſt of this congregation, in the vſe and participation of the ſame?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, if God wil, and you ſhall finde me fit for ſo holie an exerciſe, the thing alſo whiche A deſire, euen with my whole heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. <hi>Your fitnes for that purpoſe, I know not how better to diſcerne of, than by examining of you, and deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from you</hi> a reaſon, of the fayth and hope that is in you, <hi>whereunto, I aske of you firſt, whether you bee willing to ſubmit your ſelfe.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Yea in deede, with an vnfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned affection, praying you for Chriſtes
<pb facs="tcp:28033:6"/> ſake to haue regarde of mee, that in the things I knowe, I may bee ſtill further builded vp, euen vnto the age of a perfect man in Chriſt, and the thinges I am ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of, I may be inſtructed and made acquainted by your good meanes, with the Lordes trueth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. <hi>I am glad to heare you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt this care and deſire, And fith you requeſt this much of mee, I will labour what I can to ſatisfy your wiſh in both reſpects. To begin therefore, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things think you, euery good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſhuld bring with him, to the right vſe and participation of the Lords ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, that ſo he may receiue it to Gods glory, and the good and comfort of his own ſoule, both in this life preſent, and that which is to come.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer</hi> I haue hearde you your ſelfe ſaye, there are required principally fiue thinges.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest. <hi>Which are they?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Firſt, a ſounde knowledge, generally of al the will of God, as he hath reueiled the ſame in his worde, and more ſpecialy of the matter of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per:
<pb facs="tcp:28033:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> Secondly, a ſtedfaſt faith in the truth of all his promiſes, but chiefly of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> concern the forgiuenes of ſins in this life, and the hope &amp; fruition of heauen in the life to come. Thirdly, vnfeigned repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for all our iniquities, whatſoeuer, ether original or actual. Fourthly, ſincere loue towards all men &amp; euen particularly towarde our enemies. And laſtly humble thankeſgiuing to almightie God, for all his mercies and namely for thoſe that hee giueth vs, at that his holy table.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. <hi>You haue ſayd well, howbeit: both for auoyding of confuſion, and for your more full inſtruction in theſe neceſſary points, let vs deale with euery one of theſe in ſuch order, as you haue put them down, that ſo alſo I may the better perceiue, whether you vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the things you ſpeake, yea or no. And firſt for knowledg, why do you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire knowledge ſo much? will not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, good intents, mens imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or ſome od conceits of our owne heades, ſerue the turne heere?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No verely: for though in popery wee haue bene taught, that ignorance is
<pb facs="tcp:28033:7"/> the mother of deuotion: and that as wee intende, God will ſend, with many ſuch like corrupt opinions and ſpeaches, yet now knowe wee theſe aſſertions to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable and damnable, aſwel by the plain places of Scripture, whiche affirmeth, that men erre, becauſe they knowe not Gods worde: And againe, that <hi>this is life eternall to knowe GOD, to bee the onely true GOD, and him whome hee hath ſent Ieſus Christe,</hi> as by the light of humaine reaſon, for which of vs would bee igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant our ſelues in the thinges we profeſſe or approue of want of skill in others, we aſſuring our ſelues hereof, that without knowledg we cannot tel, no not in earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie matters, where to begin, how to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede, or when to make an ende. And if knowledge in worldly thinges bee ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, whereunto notwithſtanding we may be holpen a little, by the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, howe muche more is it requiſite in ſpirituall thinges, to the comprehending whereof, mans reaſon cannot reach, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be altogether inlightned by grace from aboue, the Apoſtle bearing recorde, to this, when he ſaith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the naturall man
<pb facs="tcp:28033:7"/> perceiueth not the thinges of the ſpirite of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. <hi>Why do you mention ſound knowledge.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Becauſe vnſound, corrupt or hereticall, will ſtand vs in no ſtead, to fit vs for this action, but hinder vs rather: the Apoſtle requiring deepe and due exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of our ſelues, before wee come to this miſterie, which as we cannot for want of iudgement in the naturall blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of our owne hearts, ſo can we hardly or not at all performe, when to that tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion there is added this iniquitie; of vnſound, corrupt or hereticall opinions; men in this caſe growing vnder pretext of knowledge, though not right to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne and ſtiffe defending, of their owne or other mens conceits.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. <hi>And why doe you demaund rather ſound knowledge, then perfect knowledge.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi> Becauſe wee can neuer at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine to perfection of that, or anie other good grace in this life, perfection beeing reſerued for the life that is to come: both which things the Apoſtle plainely telleth
<pb facs="tcp:28033:8"/> vs, when he ſaieth, that we know in part, &amp; propheſy in part, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which is perfect is come, then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is in parte ſhalbe aboliſhed. And yet if it be found, it is ſuch as we our ſelues may reape great comfort by, in as muche as it is Gods great gift &amp; grace freely beſtowed vpon vs, and others receiue ſome good by, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Gods graces ar not in his children, without ſome profite vnto others alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Do you meane that euery know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is meet, for fitting vs to the right and religious receiuing of this holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lords ſupper.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> No, as you maye well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue by that whiche I added, namely of the will of God reueiled in his word, for many a man maye haue ſkill in tongues, artes, manuall occupations, husbandrie, and ſuche like, and yet bee vnfit for this great purpoſe. The reaſon is this, becauſe the thing it ſelf is religious. And though therebe outward elementes vſed in it, by the Lordes appointment, yet the matter it ſelfe ment by them is ſpirituall. It muſt therefore bee a religious and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual knowledge that muſt profit vs heer,
<pb facs="tcp:28033:8"/> or elſe it will not ſerue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. <hi>Why do you ad of Gods will, and the ſame alſo reueiled in his word.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Firſt becauſe his will is the onely rule of righteouſnes and religion. Secondly, becauſe that will of his, is not made knowne vnto vs elſewhere, but in his worde, for as for thoſe ſecret things, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> belong to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord our God onely, which alſo hee hath bene pleaſed to keepe cloſe within the boſome of his owne wiſdome, as we cannot, ſo wee minde not, either to ſearche into, or to meddle with, leaſt wee be ouerwhelmed of his glory: but content our ſelues with the things reueled which belong vnto vs &amp; to all ours for euer, that we may know, beleeue, and do the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>What are the thinges, that that worde doth propound vnto vs.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> They are ſpecially two, that is faith and obedience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>What meane you by fayth?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All ſuch thinges as wee are bound to beleeue, touching our ſaluation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>What meane you by obedience?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All ſuch things as we ought to do, either towards God or man.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28033:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. <hi>Let me heare what principall points of fayth, you haue learned out of the word.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi> I beleeue in my heare, and confeſſe with my mouth, that there is but one true, eternall, immortall, inuiſible, and onely wiſe God. And that this God; or Godhead rather, is rightly diſtincted (though not deuided) into three parſons, the Father, the Sonne, and the holie ghoſt, none of them being greater or leſſe then an other, or before or after an other; in reſpect of being, honour, or time, but al of one and the ſelfe ſame ſubſtance, maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and eternitie, diſtinct notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in order and offices, for our weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſake: all their peculier workes, being yet notwithſtanding inſeperable; or to ſpeake more plainely, they in the works, that they haue wrought for vs, being not ſundered or deuided. Concerning the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the father, I beleeue and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that hee did not onely in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, by his eternall word, create of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, all thinges which are in heauen, and whiche are in earth, thinges viſible, and inuiſible, as the holy Scripture doth
<pb facs="tcp:28033:9"/> teache vs, but that alſo euer ſince the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, he hath by his almighty power and prouidence, preſerued, vphelde, and increaſed that moſte excellent worke of creation, otherwiſe, all things had long ere this, and ſhould very quickly come to end. Touching the perſon of the Sonne, I beleeue alſo and confeſſe, that he was from before all beginnings, be gotten of the father, &amp; God equall with his father, and that in the fulnes of time, hee was made man of the ſubſtance of his mother. In whom I acknowledge all his names, and chiefly theſe; Ieſus, that is to ſaye, a Sauiour, becauſe he ſhall ſaue his people from their ſinnes: and Chriſt, that is to ſay annointed, becauſe he was annointed, withall fulnes of the graces of the ſpirite by God his father, to be a King, a Prieſt, and a Prophet: his kingdome eſpeciallie ſtanding in this, that he beareth ſway in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlye in the hearts of his Children by his holy ſpirit, &amp; outwardly in his church by the ſcepter of his word: and his owne diſcipline: his Prieſthoode conſiſting in this, that hee hath offered vppe himſelfe once for all vppon the altar of the Croſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:28033:10"/> a full and ſufficient Sacrifice to God his Father, for all the ſinnes of his people, and now ſitteth at the right hand of God, making continuall requeſtes for them: his propheſie in this, that hauing in his appearing, put an ende to all manner of viſions, and reuelations whatſoeuer, hee is nowe become, the onelie Lawgiuer vnto his Churche, and therefore wll haue vs to heare none, but him onely and thoſe that ſpeake vnto vs according to him, nor to receiue any doctrine but that which he hath ſealed and ſet out vnto vs, by his worde. I confeſſe further, his two ſeuerall and diſtinct natures, of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head which hee had with his father from before all time, and the manhood, which he tooke of his mother when the fulnes of time was come, as the Apoſtle ſayeth: which two ſeuerall and diſtinct natures, beeing vnited and ioyned together make but one and the ſelfe ſame perſon Ieſus Chriſt, who is God ouer all bleſſed for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, as the Scripture witneſſeth. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I beleeue and confeſſe, that thys perſon Ieſus Chriſte GOD and man, though the Godhead can not ſuffer, and
<pb facs="tcp:28033:10"/> his manhoode could not ouercome death, did yet notwithſtandinge in his whole perſon, and not in eyther of his natures, accompliſhe and make perfect the worke of our redemption, ſuffering both in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule, the puniſhments that were due to vs for our ſinnes in bodie, as that hee was faſtened to the Croſſe, that he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and was buried in ſoule, in that hee deſcended into hell, that is to ſay, that he felt the ſharpenes of Gods wrath againſt ſinne, and dyd as it were fight hande to hand, againſt the Diuell and eternal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation ouercomming them all, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the power of his godhead for vs, that ſo wee might in bodies and ſoules bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled vnto our God,</p>
            <p>I beleeue that as hee died for our ſins, ſo the third day he roſe again according to the ſcriptures for our righteouſnes: that he viſiblie aſſcended vp into heauen, to prepare a place for vs, &amp; to take poſſeſſion of it in our name: &amp; that hee ſitteth at the right hand of his father, in al maieſty and glory, making continuall interceſſion for vs &amp; al ſaints: and that the heuens might contein him vntil the general reſtitution
<pb facs="tcp:28033:11"/> of all thinges be made, at what time hee ſhal appear with great glory, accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with infinite numbers of holy Angels and Saints, to iudge all perſons whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, which either haue died, or ſhall die before his comming, or ſhalbe founde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue at his appearing, I beleeue alſo that the holy ghoſt, is the third perſon in the deity, of the ſelfe ſame ſubſtance, Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and eternity, with the father and the ſonne, not made, created, begotten, but proceeding from them both. Whom I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg to be holy; and ſo rightly to be called, not onely becauſe he hath the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of holines in him ſelfe, but for that he is Gods ſubſtantiall and eſſentiall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to ſeale vp in our hearts Chriſts ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification and holines, and to frame vs alſo vnto hollineſſe of life, and to a godlie conuerſation.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Churche, this is that which I beleeue and profeſſe, that it is holye, becauſe it is ſanctified and made holye by Chriſt, and hath Chriſtes righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and holines imputed vnto it, and to euery ſound and faithfull member thereof, and not by reaſon of any holines
<pb facs="tcp:28033:11"/> it hath of it owne: for the Churche mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, both generall and perticuler hath erred, and may erre, yea doeth erre, and that not onelye in manners, but in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of doctrine alſo; hauing need in that reſpect continually, to flye vnto the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes of ſinnes, and dayly to ſay as our Sauiour doeth teach them, <hi>forgiue vs our treſpaſſes &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, I beleeue that this Church is Catholique, or vniuerſall, that is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed farre and wide vpon the face of the earth and ſcattered abroad thorow out al the world, and is not tied to any one place either to <hi>Affrica,</hi> as the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, or to <hi>Rome</hi> as the Papiſts ſuppoſe or to any time or ſuch like, but that God hath had, and euer will haue, in euery age &amp; nation ſome, that appertaine vnto him, howſoeuer it be, that they cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued or ſeene by mens eyes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly I beleeue, that this Church is the companye of all Gods elect, whome God hath ſingled from the reſt of the world vnto himſelf, and a felowſhip of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ones, whome the Lord hath made holy vnto himſelfe alſo: and that therefore it
<pb facs="tcp:28033:12"/> becommeth thoſe, that bee ſound and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere members of this faithfull congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, on the one ſide dayly to labour for al maner of ſanctification and holines, both in ſoule and bodie, and on the other ſide, carefully to ſtirre vp them ſelues, to haue bowels of compaſſion, and fellowlike fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, that is to weepe, with them that weepe, and to reioyce with them that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, and to bee like affectioned one of them to another, as both Gods word, and the ſtraight coniuncion that is betweene them doth require.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, I beleeue and confeſſe, that the eſſentiall notes and markes to diſcern this Churche by before men, are not (as the Papiſts imagined) antiquity, vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalitie and conſent, for they be deceitfull, agreeing manye times, to the moſt wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and vngodly aſſemblies of the worlde: beſides that being qualities, and not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunces, they cannot be eſſentiall notes to diſtinguiſhe, no more then breath or lyfe can diſcerne men from ſundrie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures: But as the truth doeth teache vs, the pure preaching of the Woorde, voyde of mans mixture, and
<pb facs="tcp:28033:12"/> the ſincere adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, without mans inuentions or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes.</p>
            <p>Concerning the worde, I allowe or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue none for it, or vnder the name of it, but onelye the Canonicall bookes of the old and new teſtament, being rightly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided into the Lawe and the Goſpell, the Law, being a doctrine deliuered vs from God, teaching vs what wee ought to do, as well towardes him, as one of vs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another: the Goſpel; being a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye doctrine alſo, inſtructing vs what we muſt beleeue to our ſaluation thorow Ieſus, Chriſt, there beeing as much diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between them, as is betweene do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and beleeuing, I heer profeſſing fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that this word is not to be read on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, but for the edification and profite of Gods people, faythfullie to bee expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and publikely preached. Concerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacraments, I allow or receiue no more but two onely, which the Lorde hath left to be had in perpetuall vſe in his church, til his comming again, that is, baptiſme, and the Lords ſupper: baptiſm ſucceding in place of circumciſion among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes
<pb facs="tcp:28033:13"/> and the Lords Supper comming in ſtead of the Iewiſh paſſeouer.</p>
            <p>Baptiſme witneſſeth and pledgeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs diuers things: as firſt our entrance into the bodie of Chriſte, whiche is his Churche, in whiche reſpect it is admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to new borne babes, euen preſenlye vpon their byrth. Secondly, it is a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of our regeneration begunn in vs, and that we are become as it were newe borne babes vnto God our heauenly, Fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther. Thirdly, it ſealeth vnto vs, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes and waſhing away of our ſinnes, in the ſacrifice of Chriſtes death. Laſtly, it repreſenteth vnto vs this muche, that wee being baptized into Chriſtes death, ſhould by the power thereof die vnto ſin, and that by the vertue of his reſurrection (a ſure pleadge alſo whereof wee haue in our Baptiſme) we ſhould walke in new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of life. All whiche thinges teach vs alſo this much further, that for as much as Chriſts ſacrifice was but once perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and our entrie into the Church, is but once made &amp;c, that therefore this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, is but once to bee adminiſtred either to the infantes of beleeuing. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,
<pb facs="tcp:28033:13"/> or elſe to thoſe that beeing of the yeares of diſcretion, are comanded to the faith, and able to render a reaſon of their hope, and that religion that they are new<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lie entred into.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe the Lordes Supper to bee a pleadge of that ſpirituall ſtrength and bleſſed continuaunce, that we haue in the holy fellowſhip of the bodie of Chriſt, the Lorde ſealing vp thereby further in our hearts, firſt, the death and paſſion of our Sauiour Chriſt, together with the fruits and benefites wee receiue thereby, and namely the forgiuenes of our ſinnes. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that ſpirituall nouriſhment that wee haue by him and in him, wee beeing fed thereby, taking holde of him thorow fayth, both in ſoule and bodie, to the hope of euerlaſting life. Thirdly, that miſticall vnion, that is betwixt Chriſte and his Churche, hee dwelling in our heartes by fayth, and wee thereby being made mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his bodye, of his fleſhe, and of his bones. Laſtly, that holy bande of vnitie and loue, that ought to bee amongeſt the members of the Churche, in as muche as they though they be manie being yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:28033:14"/> partakers of one bread, are become one bodie in Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> In all which reſpects, I ſay that it ought oftentimes to bee vſed, that in due examination of themſelues do labour vnfeignedly to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare themſelues to ſo holy miſteries.</p>
            <p>Further I confeſſe, that God to this church, hath giuen vs neceſſary helps and means, for the repreſſing of euil, &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of good, the ciuil Magiſtrates, &amp; the eccleſiaſticall miniſtery, the on by the word, and the other by the ſworde, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance Gods glory, &amp; to further the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mens ſoules, euen in this life.</p>
            <p>I beleeue that to the ciuill magiſtrate, we do owe vnto the Lord, &amp; for the Lord, not onelye our goodes and riches, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal the Lord himſelfe hath bleſſed vs, but our ſelues, and our liues alſo, whiche hee hath giuen vs, becauſe that by them wee receiue from Gods hande, not onely publike peace, and quiet poſſeſſion, of our own ſubſtance, but euen the very religion and ſeruice of our God. And therfore they are ouermuch deceiued, who go about to diſpiſe gouernment, much more they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in deuor to ouerthrow it, becauſe they labor
<pb facs="tcp:28033:14"/> the confuſion of Common-wealthes and countries, and the vtter ruine and decaye of Gods feare and worſhip.</p>
            <p>Touching the eccleſiaſticall miniſtery, I beleeue and acknowledge, that nowe there are no more ordinary offices, for the execution of it, but paſtors and teachers, who ought to be men, both of ſuch life, &amp; behauiour, and alſo of ſuch learning, and iudgment, as gods word requireth, whoſe dutie ſtandeth not, in bare reading of the word alone, but in preaching the ſame vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the people; the paſtor exhorting, admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing, and reprouing, with all long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering and doctrine, adding therunto the adminiſtration of ſacraments, and publik praiers acording to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> order of the church: and the doctor propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding ſound doctrin and mightelye conuincing or confuting erronious opinions.</p>
            <p>I beleue &amp; confeſſe, that to this church. God hath giuen moſt large promiſes of grace and goodnes, all which alſo he will in conuenient time moſt mercifullye and faithfully perform, &amp; namely theſe perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars folowing amongeſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> reſt, firſt the free pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ful forgiuenes of al our ſins,
<pb facs="tcp:28033:15"/> whether it bee our originall iniquities, wherein wee were conceiued, and borne, and which we haue brought with vs into the worlde from our mothers wombe, or our actuall tranſgreſſions committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God &amp; his lawes, either by thoght, word, or deed, either by doing euil things forbidden, or by leauing vndoone good things commanded (Againſt both which) wee haue a double remedie in Chriſte; namely, that our euil committed, is remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in Chriſts death, &amp; the good that we haue or do omitte, is anſwered in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Chriſtes righteouſneſſe and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes imputed vnto vs: whiche thing as is ſerueth verie wel to expreſſe our common miſerie, and maye bee a profitable argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnfeignedly to humble vs, ſo doth it highlye commend Gods infinite mercie, freelie without any merrites or deſerts of ours at all, pardoning all our tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whiche ought not onelye to giue comfort vnto vs, in as muche as neither ſinne, the Diuell, nor hell, can laye anye thing to our charge, to take any hold vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs at all, to ouerthrowe vs, but alſo to prouoke vs to continuall thankfulnes,
<pb facs="tcp:28033:15"/> for this great loue, with care and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, walking before him all the daies of our liues, euen as thoſe that poſſeſſe holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>A ſecond ſpeciall grace, that God hath promiſed vnto his Churche, is the riſing againe of the body, at the generall iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which though it hath ben diſſolued into the duſt, ſhall yet notwithſtanding at the laſt day, by the almightie power of God, whereby hee is able to ſubdue all things vnto himſelfe, be raiſed vp again, and vnited euerie bodie vnto his owne ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall ſoule, that ſo both bodye and ſoule being ioyned together, the faithfull that in both of them, hath bene partakers of griefe in this life, maye in both of them enter into the ioyes of there Lord, and be made perfecte partakers of eternall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe.</p>
            <p>And this is the third grace, and gift of God towardes his Church which we call alſo eternall or euerlaſting life, the very ende of our faith and hope in whiche the Lorde hath layd vp for thoſe that bee his, ſuch ioies, as the eie of man hath not ſeen neither his eare hearde, neither is his
<pb facs="tcp:28033:16"/> tongue able to expreſſe, nor his hart large inough to conceiue. And this is that ſum of religion, whiche I haue learned out of the word of God, renouncing all errours &amp; opinions whatſoeuer contrarye to this, and promiſing and propoſing, by Gods good aſſiſtaunce (without whome I can not do any thing) to ſtand euen in life and death vnto this for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>It is well, and I am glad to heare this much from you, touching the firſt part of the word, namely faith: now let me heare what you can ſay concerning obedience.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Euen that that God himſelf hath put downe in the ten commaundements conteining the ſum of all our duties<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther towardes the Lorde himſelfe, in the foure commaundements of the firſt table: or one of vs towardes another conteined in the ſix commaundements of the ſecond table.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. <hi>As you haue gone ouer the groundes of religion, deliuering the ſame, in a ſhort ſumme, by which I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciue, what you hold touching faith: ſo I would haue you to declare what God
<pb facs="tcp:28033:16"/> forbiddeth and commandeth in euery co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of theſe ten, that ſo I may perceiue what growth you haue made, in the right vnderſtanding of them.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> I will gladly doo it (Sir) according to my poore ſkill. In the firſt, God doth forbid vs to allow in our iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, vſe in our actions, or defend in our wordes, anye idolatrie, ſouthſaying, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juring, witchcraft, charming, falſe doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, mans inuentions, feare, loue, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation, of any whatſoeuer creature a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue God, or equallie with him or anye perſon or perſons whatſoeuer, which ſhal approoue, vſe, or maintaine ſuch things; commanding vs on the other ſide, to yeeld vnto him his due honor, and ſeruice both outwardlye, and inwardly, that is, to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, loue, feare, &amp; obey him in al things, to worſhippe him onely, to put our whole truſt in him onely in al feare, danger, and neceſſitie, to fly vnto him alone, &amp; to call vpon him only, acknowledging him alone to be the creator, preſeruer, and gouernor of al things, both in heauen and in earth, and in places vnder the earth, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In the ſeconde, hee forbiddeth all
<pb facs="tcp:28033:17"/> making of images, or procuring of them to bee made, to expreſſe or reſemble hys incomprehenſible maieſtie by, as alſo the allowaunce, vſe or defence, of anye ſuche Images, or any other thing whatſoeuer, by which we minde to ſeeke him, or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe him in the ſame, togeather with a manner of ſuperſtition whatſoeuer, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh, Iewiſh, or Papiſticall, wee ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaining altogether in his holye ſeruice, from our owne inuentions, blind deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, humaine doctrines, and other mens examples or rules, as alſo from ſuppoſed good intents, &amp; other ſuch like corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whatſoeuer, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manding vs againe to giue vnto him that manner of worſhip and ſeruice onelie, which hee himſelfe in his word requireth, without adding ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, or taking from it, becauſe hee know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what beſt agreeth, with his own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, according whereunto alſo hee hath giuen vs a perfect rule of righteouſneſſe, we continually withdrawing our ſelues from all ſuperſtitions and carnall imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, as wel concerning his ſpirituall maieſty, &amp; ſubſtance, as alſo touching the ſeruices that we are to perform vnto him.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28033:17"/>
            <p>In the third, hee condemneth all vſing or abuſing, of his reuerende and fearefull name, either vainly, or in raſh ſwearing, (be they othes) witchcraft, curſſing, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwearing, and ſuch like, yea, hee forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs to talke, ſpeake, or thinke of him himſelfe, his word, his workes, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer elſe hee is made knowne vnto vs by, without an vrgent &amp; weighty cauſe, or without great reuerence and feare, of his dreadfull maieſtie, he commaunding vs agayne, to haue and vſe in moſte high reuerence his holy name, and al the parts and peeces of it, his workes, word, ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and whatſoeuer elſe he is known vnto vs by: likewiſe to take an othe, (but yet vſing therein, with great reuerence the fearefull &amp; glorious name of our God onelye, and of no creature whatſoeuer) when there is iuſt occaſion, as to affirme or mainteine a trueth, (eſpeciallie if the magiſtrate lawfully require or command it) to ſette foorth the glorie of God, and to preſerue mutuall agreement and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlye charitie amongeſt men, alwaies perſwading our ſelues, for the better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of theſe duties, that hee is
<pb facs="tcp:28033:18"/> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only ſeatcher of hates, &amp; rewarder of all ſincerity &amp; truth, as on the other ſide alſo, moſt ſharp &amp; fearful reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of al hipocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, blaſphemy, fals &amp; vain ſwearing, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with al other prophanings &amp; abuſings of his moſt bleſſed name &amp; religion what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, how great or ſmal ſo euer they be.</p>
            <p>In the fourth he forbiddeth, all abuſing of the Lords day, eſpecially, by doing of our owne wils in it, or by ſpeaking of our owne wordes, or by delight in diſcourſe or dealing with worldly matters, though at other times lawfull, by vſing alſo any wicked or vngodly exerciſe whatſoeuer, as dauncing, dicing, carding, table-play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, cauerne or alehouſe haunting, refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the beholding of interludes, be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bayting or ſuch like, or by abuſing of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations, at other times moderately v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of them ſelues lawfull, as ſhooting, bowling, riding, &amp;c. And commandeth vs on the other ſide reuerendly &amp; religiouſly to ſpend the ſabbothes, as in ceaſing from the honeſt labors of our chriſtian callings and in abſteining from lawful exerciſes or recreations, ſo in preparing our ſelues, to and in frequenting &amp; vſing of godly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes,
<pb facs="tcp:28033:18"/> both publicke and priuate. By publicke, I means the church aſſemblies, to which we ſhould carefully ioyne, our ſelues, and ſoberlie and quietlie ther be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue our ſelues, in humble confeſſion of our ſines, in open profeſſing of our faythe; in vnfeigned thankeſgiuing for mercies receiued, in earneſt prayer for graces that we want, in diligent and attentiue hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the word, read and preached, and in chriſtian communicating in the holye Sacramentes, as time and occaſion ſhall ſerue, with carefull performance of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther duties whatſoeuer, and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye charitable releife to the poore, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allye ſith God hath giuen vs in his great mercy, a time, a place and quietnes, and abilitye, both of bodye and minde, to the ende wee ſhould the better attend, theſe publike exerciſes of Gods holy religion. And when theſe be finiſhed, to beſtow the reſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time in meditating by our ſelues vpon the things taught and hard in confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the ſame with other our brethren in examinyng vpon the ſame, our wiues, children, &amp; ſeruaunts, that ſo we may lay it vp in our hearts, for the ſtrengthening
<pb facs="tcp:28033:19"/> of our faith, &amp; the directing of our liues. And yet not to ceaſe here, but theſe duties perfourmed, to giue our ſelues to priuate reading of Gods word, to Chriſtian prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and calling vpon his name, to earneſt conſideration of his moſt noble and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull workes: to viſit the ſicke, and the priſoners, ſpecially ſuch as ſuffer for righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teous cauſes, that as the day is dedicated to ſpirituall endes, ſo it may altogether be ſpent in ſpiritual exerciſes, and as it was ordeined for Gods glorye, and our good, ſo it may wholly be referred to the ſame.</p>
            <p>In the fifth commaundement, the Lord forbiddeth al rebellion and diſobedience, euill ſpeech, or wicked thoughtes, of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, miniſters, maſters, dames, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or any other perſon, whom the lord in his wiſedome and goodnes hath made our ſuperiours, either by age, aucthority, office, wealth, or any other maner of way whatſoeuer: hee commaunding againe (becauſe al aucthoritye, whether it be of magiſtrates, miniſters, parentes, &amp;c. is from himſelfe) that we ſhoulde vſe hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble obedience towards them all, beating
<pb facs="tcp:28033:19"/> a reuerend minde to them, being ready to relieue, aſſiſt, and aide them to our vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, with our goodes, bodies, and liues, and willing to do after their commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in all things, in the Lord, and for the Lord according to our duties.</p>
            <p>In the ſixt, there is condemned al mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, bloudſheading, fighting, quarreling, brauling and chiding, as alſo all hatred, malice, and enuie in the heart, togeather with haſtie and headleſſe ſpeeches, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery thing whatſoeuer, that may prouoke others or ſtirre vp our ſelues thereto, yea, there is forbidden all manner of deſire to do hurt or to reuenge: On the other ſide, there is commaunded, vnfeigned loue, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience, humilitie, humanitie, keeping and making of peace, gentle wordes, ſoft aunſwers, and all dueties of compaſſion whatſoeuer, more perticulerlie the relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of ſuche as bee in neede, the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of ſuch as bee in diſtreſſe, and the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and ſuccouring of them that bee in daunger, in perſon, life, health, name &amp;c. to the vttermoſt of our powers.</p>
            <p>The ſeuenth condemning al whordom, fornication, adultry, inceſt together with
<pb facs="tcp:28033:20"/> baudy and filthy talke, all loue ſongs, tic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, toyings, danſing, &amp; all other wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton or light behauiour and vnſeemely ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, in body or countenance (which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are nothing els but violent prouoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to filthines and euill, together with all vncleanes both of body and minde, on the other ſide, it inioyneth vs, to keep our veſſels in honor, and holines, as the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, and the temples of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt, and to profeſſe and practiſe alſo all purenes and chaſtity, not only as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the act, but alſo in heart, word, and behauiour, that ſo wee maye ſanctifie the Lorde, both in our ſoules &amp; bodies, which are his, he allowing vs alſo by this lawe, euen for the auoiding of all incontinency, his own holy ordinance of marriage, ſo it be made vp and performed in him.</p>
            <p>The eight forbiddeth all theft and ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, either openlye or ſecretly, either by force, fraude, or otherwiſe, together with all deceaueable buying and ſelling, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be in euil wares, or by falſ weights and meaſures, alſo al vſury, all extortion, all oppreſſion, al bribry, all vncharitable getting &amp; keeping of other mens goods,
<pb facs="tcp:28033:20"/> and all manner of corrupt dealing what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, as couſinage, commendation of deceitfull commodities, &amp;c. On the other ſide it commandeth vs, all true and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dealing in our ſeuerall callings, due payment of debtes, diligent ſeruice, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all careful and friendly ſauing and deliuering of other mens goods, wee contenting our ſelues with our preſent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, &amp; not repining at the bleſſinges of god vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other men, in inward or outward graces whatſoeuer preferred before vs.</p>
            <p>The ninth forbiddeth manifeſt periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, &amp; breaking of lawfull othes and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, all lying, ſlaundering, backbiting talecarrying, flattering and diſſembling, together with all euill ſpeaking againſt others, and particularly diſcouering our brothers ſecrets, either in words, or wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, proceding from the malice &amp; nagh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines of mans heart. Againe, it comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs to maintein the honor and credit of all, ſpecially thoſe that be aduanced to publke place, in the Church or common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth &amp; in al our ſpeeches to be iuſt, ſim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, modeſt, louing, &amp;c. as alſo to witnes, iudg &amp; ſpeak the truth, yea y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole truth,
<pb facs="tcp:28033:21"/> and nothing elſe but the trueth (yet with a ſanctified minde and mouth) as occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhalbe offred, without any reſpect, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching al men and matters whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>In the tenth and laſt commaundement, the Lord condemneth the very pricks and motions to ſinne in mens minde (whiche the ſcripture ſometimes calleth the luſts &amp; concupiſcences of our curſſed nature) as alſo all diſcontentednes of heart, with the ſtate and condicion that God is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to put vs in, together with all mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſting therof, by vnlawful wiſhes, which be after a ſorte, thinges inſeperable, clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to the ſinnes of luſt, and diſconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tednes of minde, forbidden heere. And heere he commandeth vs to fight againſt the beginnings of euil, in the firſt aſſaut, leaſt otherwiſe, temptation further pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailing vpon vs with delight, we be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on forwarde by the ſubtiltie of ſinne, both to conſent vnto the euill, &amp; to ſtriue for the attempting and accompliſhment hereof. Yea, hee commaundeth vs to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and make muche of ſuche good moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as hee putteth in our minds, not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering them to die or to be quenched tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
<pb facs="tcp:28033:21"/> the corruption and naughtines of our owne heartes, but carefully to ſtriue by all holy meanes, and the diligent and often vſe of the ſame, with earneſtnes to purſue them, and to bring them to good effect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest. <hi>I can not but reioyce in the things I hear you ſpeake, and approue of the ſame as good and holy: Howbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, becauſe in the beginning you ſayd, that beſides the general knowledge of Gods will reueiled in his worde, there was required ſpecially knowledge, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the matter of the Lords ſupper, let vs deale ſomewhat in that alſo. Into whiche before wee enter perticulerly, I would gladly know of you, what a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> An outward and holy ſigne, ordeined by God himſelfe, and appointed to be vſed in and of his church, to ſignifie and ſeale vnto the faith of the beleeuers there, ſuch things as cannot be ſeene with mortall eie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Why do you call it an outwarde ſigne, and yet holy withall.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Outwarde, becauſe it is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect
<pb facs="tcp:28033:22"/> to our ſenſes, as ſight, feeling, taſte: and holy, becauſe it is appointed for holy vſes, and to ſignifie moſt holy things vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>And why do you ſay, ordeined by God himſelfe.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it belongeth to none, but to him alone, to ordeine holye ſignes and Sacraments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>And why ſay you, appointed to be vſed, in and of his Church.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Firſt, to auoyde all priuate adminiſtration of them: Secondly to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that ſuperſtition in popery, of ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them without participation and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating in them: thirdly to declare to whom they belong, namely, to the church and to none other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. <hi>What meane the words fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, in this diſcription of a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> They conteine and expreſſe, one principal end of the inſtitution of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, namely that they bee ordeined to be ſeales and pledges of excellent things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>To what endes els, hath God or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined, ſuch holy ſignes &amp; ſacraments.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28033:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Thereby more and more to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe our dulnes and groſſenes, ſpecially in comprehending of ſpirituall, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly matters, and withall to ſtrengthen and aſſure our weake faith in the trueth and certaintie of his moſt ſweete promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>How many thinges are there to be conſidered in a Sacrament.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Three ſpeciallye, as I take it: namely the outward Element it ſelfe, or the viſible and ſenſible ſigne: Secondly, the inward and ſpirituall grace, ſignified thereby: and laſtly, the analogie and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion betweene the ſigne, and the thing ſignified.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>What be the ſignes or elements in the Lordes Supper.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> We haue there, two moſt liuely ſignes, to wit, Bread, and Wine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>What is the ſpirituall and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde grace.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Chriſte and all his merrites, in whome alone dwelleth the fulnes of all goodnes and truth for euermore.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>What proportion is there, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe ſigns, &amp; the thing ſignified.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28033:23"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi> The bread ſpecially, when it is broken, doth ſignify vnto me Chriſts body crucified for mee, and the wine doth liuely repreſent vnto me, his moſt preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bloud that was ſhed for mee, and for many, to the forgiuenes of ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. <hi>What ment the Lord to take theſe elements rather then other, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent &amp; ſet out ſuch excellent things by.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi> Becauſe they do indeed moſt liuely declare, thoſe ſpiritual graces, that we haue from Chriſt: for as bread ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theneth mans heart, and Wine comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the ſame, as both the trueth of the worde and dailye experience teacheth; ſo muſt we haue all ſpirituall ſtrength and conſolation for our ſoules, from Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and him crucified and bruiſed, and broken for our ſinnes, or elſe it will not bee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>And wherefore hath he ordeined two ſignes, in his holy ſupper, ſeeing in baptiſme there is but one onely.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Not onely to meete with that ſacriligious deuiſe of popery, taking from the people the Cup: but more liuely to ſet
<pb facs="tcp:28033:23"/> foorth his loue towardes vs in the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of his mercies, and the more ſtead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly to aſſure vs, that he as in ſpirituall reſpects, doth not feede vs to the halues, but fully, the aboundance of his graces in Chriſt, being not onely the meat, but the drincke alſo of our ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>And why hath the Lord appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted you, to take, eate, and drinke, theſe outward elements.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The more aſſuredly therby to put me in poſſeſſion of Chriſt, and his merits, and the fruites and effectes flowing from the ſame, I being no more certein in my outward man, that I haue receiued theſe to ſome good profite and purpoſe, then that by faith, I haue certeinly taken hold of Chriſt, hee dwelling in my heart by the ſame, and making me fruitfull to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good worke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Do you meane that you ſhoulde much regard the outward elements? or that the breade and wine are become our ſpirituall nouriſhment.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> No indeede, neither the one nor the other: for if we doubt vppon the outward, we ſhould ſoone haue our faith
<pb facs="tcp:28033:24"/> ſtolen away from the inward. And for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we know &amp; beleeue, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodily things cannot nouriſh ſpiritualy, but this is that that I mean, that by the outward ſignes, we ſhuld be as it wer led by the hand vnto that which they ſignifie, from whence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, both ſpiritual life heer, &amp; eternal life in the world to come do proceed, that is to ſay, Chriſt Ieſus himſelf who hath ſuffred his death &amp; paſſion, to take away the cauſe of our death &amp; condemnation, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye, Sinne, and to renue vs vnto eternall life, through the fulnes of all ſpiritual liueli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which reſteth and remaineth in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Where is Ieſus Chriſte now (the matter of the Supper) ſpecially accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his humaine nature.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Not on earth ſurely, whatſoeuer men fantaſie, but in heauen from whence he ſhall come in great glory, to iudge the quicke and the dead.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>By what means, can you the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ar on earth, receue him that is in heuen.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> As I receiue with my hande &amp; my mouth the ſacrament, that is to ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread &amp; wine, of the ſacrament, &amp; that to the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment of this body, and preſeruation of
<pb facs="tcp:28033:24"/> natural life: euen ſo, by the vertue &amp; pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt, I do in wardly &amp; in my ſoul, receiue &amp; imbrace, thorow the hande &amp; mouth of a liuely and ſtedfaſt faith, our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, verie God and verie man, that by him, I may leade a ſpiritual life heere, and afterwards liue eternally.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Hytherto we haue laboured, and I hope profitablye, in the firſt parte of preparation to the Lords ſupper: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alſo (becauſe it is the foundation and groundworke to the reſt) we haue delt more largely. Now let vs proceed to the other remaining, dealing with them in ſome more ſhorter ſort, yet ſo ſtil, as we may comfortablie and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablie vnderſtande the ſame. Tell mee therfore which is the ſecond thing, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily required of him, that ſhal wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely partake in this holy ſacrament of the body and bloud of the Lord.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> A ſteadfaſt faith in the trueth of Gods promiſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Why do you ſo expreſly demand ſteadfaſtnes in fayth.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Becauſe that is moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilye required in the ſame, as a notable
<pb facs="tcp:28033:25"/> mean to make it being Gods gift, in ſom meaſure acceptable before him, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable to our owne ſoules: for what ioy or peace can wee haue when our perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions be carried hither and thither and we find our ſelues wauering in thoſe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall thoughts of our hearts, that do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne Gods eternall mercies towards vs in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>And why do you require a ſtead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt faith, rather then a perfecte faith, ſeeing that perfection beeing more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, then ſteadfaſtnes, it is likelye that it ſhould bring forth more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent fruites.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer</hi> Becauſe that we, by reaſon of the remainders of corruptions, that wee ſhall carrie about with vs, ſo long as we liue heere, can neuer in this life atteine to perfection, of this or any other ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all grace. And yet if it be ſteadfaſt, ſure, and vnmooueable, it is ſuch as God will accept in vs for Chriſts ſake, becauſe ther is in him alone, matter ſufficient to cure all our maladies, and to couer all our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections: and ſuche alſo as wee maye well comforte our ſelues in, becauſe hee
<pb facs="tcp:28033:25"/> that only giueth faith, hath bene pleaſed to beſtow the ſame vpon vs, and wee reſt perſwaded, that hee will not reiecte hys owne worke in vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Do you mean, by a ſteadfaſt and an vnmooueable faith, ſuch a fayth, as from the firſt planting of it, was neuer aſſaulted with diffidence, or ſhaken with diſtruſt.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> No indeede: for that were to imagine, that there were no ſinne remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in vs, or ſathan without vs to tempt, whereas wee knowe, that as in reſpect of our ſelues, wee are dull of heart, and ſlow to beleeue, ſo Sathan in a continuall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice againſt vs, hath not onely deſired to winnow vs as wheate, but ſore battered and beaten our faith and hope. Howbeit heer is our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, that Chriſt hath praied for vs, that our faith faile not, we further raiſing vp alſo our ſelues, euen as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle doeth him ſelfe, and the reſt of the beleeuers, with this ſweete ſentence, that though wee doubt, yet wee diſpaire not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>And what do you take this ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt fayth to bee, that you ſpeake of.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> It is a certaine perſwaſion, and
<pb facs="tcp:28033:26"/> particular application of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whol word, &amp; ſpecially of the ſweet &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes therin conteined, to mine own hart. I aſſuredly feeling this in my ſoul, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is generally promiſed, to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithful &amp; beleuing people, ſhalbe particularly verified, &amp; ſpecialy in my ſelf</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>And why ſay you that by the eie of faith, you look rather to the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, then to the whole worde, or holye ſcriptures of God.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe though it be true, that my faith reſpecteth al the word, &amp; euery part &amp; peece of it, as which conteineth whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is neceſſary to eternall life, yet doth it moſt principally regarde the promiſes therein comprized, which be indeede, the moſt proper peculier, and comfortable ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eicts therof, as which do moſt liuely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; ſet before vs Gods eternal fauor, Chriſtes holie merrites, and whatſoeuer elſe is ſweet and pleaſant, either for this life preſent, or that which is to come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Are all promiſes in the worde, of like excellency, ſweetnes, and comfort.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No certainly, for though that they bee all profitable, yet the promiſes of
<pb facs="tcp:28033:26"/> ſpiritual bleſſings ar moſt to be eſteemed</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>If all be not a like precious, tell mee which are thoſe promiſes, that you ought to make moſt ſpeciall account of, to lay hold of them by faith.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hand of faith, I ought to aprehend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al general, whether they concern, earthly, or heauenly, bodilye, or ſpirituall benefits, becauſe they be the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry noriſhment, or life rather of my ſoule: howbeit, I ought moſt chiefly to look vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe, that do concern the forgiuenes of my ſins in this life thorow chriſts obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, &amp; thoſe that are made touching eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, &amp; euerlaſting ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> throw him</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>And why ſhuld you regard theſe rather then the other.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe without the feeling of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forgiuenes of our ſinns in Chriſt, we can haue nothing but diſquietnes of ſpirit, &amp; hel in our hearts, neither can all or any of Gods graces without that, be comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto vs: but means rather to agrauate our moſt fearful conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation. And beſids if it wer not for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruition of eternal life, after this life ended, we y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> profeſſe godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, were the moſt miſerable of all men.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28033:27"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>I perceiue then by this, that as it behooueth euery godly man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, to be well acquainted with all the word generally, ſo it ſpecially ſtandeth them in hand, to labor to haue a moſt skilful feeling in the promiſes thereof.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That is moſt true, as without the which indeede he cannot, either lawfully enioye, or religiouſlye vſe, the outwarde bleſſinges of this life or patiently vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe, or couragiouſlie ouercome, the afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that he is to endure for Chriſts ſake, or comfortablie to feele Gods moſt holie fauour and loue, or ſweetly be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of Chriſt and his merites, or haue anye hope of heauen aſſuredlye ſettled in his heart, or atteine indeede to any true ioy and conſolation of the ſpirite, becauſe all and euery one of theſe things are offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and as it were conueied ouer vnto vs, in the promiſes of the word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>But wee are dull of heart, and ſlow to beleeue, as you ſaid before. And beſides there ſtandeth betwixt vs and Gods promiſes, not onely the cloud of our natural corruption, but alſo the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable tranſgreſſions that we haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb facs="tcp:28033:27"/> againſte God, and one of vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another, by meanes whereof, we are become not onely vnmeet and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of any ſuch grace, but in ſtead of the ſame, haue deſerued all iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, both temporall and eternall, to be powred forth vpon vs. To all which adde the exact iuſtice of God, whiche cannot but puniſh ſuch horrible tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions. In this miſerable eſtate and taking what ſhall wee do? or what ſhall betide of vs.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I will ſhew you ſo far forth as my poore ſkill will ſerue mee, and as I haue learned from your mouth out of the word againſt the ſtrength of naturall corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in our ſelues, wee are to ſet the power of our regeneration from GOD, Gods worke in the excellency &amp; might of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to ouerthrow euerye thing, that either by our weakenes, or Sathans ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, ſhall exalt it ſelfe againſt it. And to the wound that is made in vs by the huge heape of our tranſgreſſions, we are to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie the ſoueraigne ſalue of our ſauiours ſufferinges and death, the leaſt crumme or drop as you would ſaye of whoſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
<pb facs="tcp:28033:28"/> is able to break the ſtrongeſt band &amp; chain of our ſins, in whome alſo being the perſon that god is wel pleaſed with, &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the fulnes of al goodnes in himſelf, we cannot but find ſufficient worthines, to couer our wretchednes &amp; all imperfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ious that be in vs whatſoeuer. And as for Gods iuſtice, it is all ready anſwered in Chriſts obedience for vs, by the meanes wherof alſo ther is an entrance made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infinit treſure houſe &amp; ſtore of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible mercy, to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated vnto vs. And if it agree not with humain equity wher a det is once paid, to demand it again, can we imagin y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhal ſtand w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Gods iuſtice, either to demand y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> det, or to caſt vs into priſon, ſich y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hand writing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, which was againſt vs to condemn vs, is canceled thruogh chriſts obedience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>But many of Gods children, in the middeſt of ther co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bats, know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they haue faith or no: yea, for the moſt part it ſemeth to them, that then they haue non at all. Tell me therefore how may a godly man trie, whether he haue faith, yea, or no.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They muſt here haue recourſe, to
<pb facs="tcp:28033:28"/> thoſe fruits and effects of faith, that God hath bin pleaſed to beſtow vpon them, &amp; inabled the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſom meaſure to ſhew forth either towards his owne maieſtye, or to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men, &amp; particularly they muſt look to thoſe graces of feruent praier, chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an patience, godly ſorrow, ſincere loue, &amp; many ſuch other good duties, either paſt or preſent, as God hath made them able, either in affection to deſire &amp; aproue, or in action to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſh &amp; perform; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence doutles they may &amp; ought to receiue com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort, becauſe that if our former tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions proceding from our ſelues, ſhuld caſt vs down &amp; grieue vs to the hart, then the former feelings of gods Graces beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon vs of his own goodnes, &amp; flowing only &amp; wholy from him, ſhould giue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to our ſoules, &amp; yeeld vs hope in time to come, though preſently we find it not, that we ſhal again poſſeſſe, not only theſe former ioyes, but greater meaſure and more aſſurance thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>One neceſſary queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is yet behind, wherein alſo I would gladlye haue you ſpeak namely, why you do require faith now, rather then at other tims ſith wee ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:28033:29"/> carefully indeuour alwaies, to find and feele, that at home in owne hearts, as which is indeed the principal comfortt and ioy of our ſoules.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Becauſe we haue now thorow the vſe of the Sacrament, in more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and plaine manner, all Chriſtes mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites offered vnto vs, yea, whole Chriſte himſelfe, in whome all the promiſes of God, are Yea, and Amen. Al which, ſith they can no otherwiſe bee laide holde of, then by the hand of faith, (for Chriſt is in heauen, and we are on earth, and his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are ſpiritual, and cannot but by a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall inſtrument be apprehended, and faith onely hath this vertue in it, to ioyn thinges together, that be as far a ſunder as heauen and earth, yea, and to make things paſt, and to come alſo, as though they were actually preſent, either in ſight or poſſeſſion) I ſaye wee haue now more neede, then at other times to raiſe and ſtirre vp our faith, and more ſtrongly and comfortably, to applie the promiſes vnto our owne ſoules, or elſe we ſhalbe farre of from aunſwering the goodnes offered, a great diſhonor doutles to almighty God.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28033:29"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Whiche is the third poynt, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceceſſay for a godly communicant, to bring with him to the right vſe &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of the Lords holy Supper?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Vnfeigned repentance for all his ſinnes whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Why do you demand vnfeigned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in repentance?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To the end that our inward and outward hipocriſie, both before God and man, (a vice too common in all holy acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and euen in this particularly) being put farre from vs, wee might labour in ſoundneſſe to performe that, that ſhalbe acceptable in his ſight, and profitable and comfortable both to our ſelues, &amp; others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Why do you demaund vnfeined repentance, rather then perfect?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi> Becauſe as hath bene ſayde ſundry times before, we can neuer in this life atteine to perfection, either of thys, or of anye other good grace whatſoeuer. And yet if it be ſettled in the heart, and proceede in ſinceritie from the ſame (the heart being the moſt principall part, that God requireth in all ſeruices) it cannot but be accepted in his ſight.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28033:30"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>And what profite ſhal come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, by this vnfeigned repentaunce, if vpon right examination of our ſelues, wee finde it in our own ſoules?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, it ſhall diſtinguiſh vs from Hipocrites, who outwardly make manye godly ſhewes of this, &amp; other good things alſo, but yet haue no ſoundnes within them. Secondly, it ſhalbe a ſure pledge vnto vs, of the forgiuenes of our ſins, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe repentaunce &amp; forgiuenes of ſinnes can neuer be ſundered, as the Scripture ſayth in manye places. Thirdlie it is an euident teſtimony, that wee haue imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Goſpell, (becauſe repentaunce is a principall part of it) and by conſequent eternall life, becauſe the Goſpell is the power of God to ſaluation, to all them that beleeue; Laſtly, it is a plaine proofe of that faith, that God by his worde out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly and by his ſpirite inwardly, hath wrought in our hearts, repentaunce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one principall fruit and effect there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. <hi>What is this repentaunce it ſelfe?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> An earneſt hatred of all and
<pb facs="tcp:28033:30"/> euerye ſinne, whiche heeertofore wee haue loued, delighted in, or perfourmed, and on the other ſide, an vnfeigned loue of all righteouſneſſe whatſoeuer, whiche heeretofore wee haue hated: this loue of the good, and hatred of the euill, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from a right and reuerent feare of Gods eternall Maieſtie, and working al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſo farre in vs, that it cauſeth vs to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake our ſelues, and to ſtriue in ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable meaſure to the mortification of our owne corruption, and to the renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Gods Image in vs, to the end we may be altogether gouerned by the holye ſpirite of God, both in the ſeruice of his Maieſtie, and alſo in the performance of all holy duties towardes our ſelues and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. <hi>I perceiue by this you haue ſayed, that before wee can eyther tell what repentaunce is, or can well come to the practiſe of it, wee muſte bee acquainted, and that in feeling, with manye good thinges, and name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, that wee muſte knowe firſte what ſinne is, alſo howe manye ſortes there are of it, and likewiſe by howe
<pb facs="tcp:28033:31"/> many meanes it may bee committed. Tell me therefore firſt, what you take ſinne to bee?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Sinne is the tranſgreſſion and breach of the law of God onely.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>And why ſaye you, it is a breach of Gods law onelie?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Both becauſe his law is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie rule of all religion towardes him, and of all charitie towards men, and becauſe none hath authoritie to binde mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences with the cordes of ſinne, but hee alone, that hath made them, and who one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knoweth what ſinne is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Howe many ſortes of ſinnes are there?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Two kindes as I take it: the one originall, and the other actuall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>What call you Originall ſinne?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> An vniuerſal infection and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all corruption of al mankind, both in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye and ſoule, conueied ouer from our firſt parents <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Heuah,</hi> (becauſe we were all in their loynes ſtanding and falling together with them) not by imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, but by purgation, into al their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie, there flowing from the ſame, an
<pb facs="tcp:28033:31"/> vtter defacing of Gods Image in vs, which was giuen vs thorow his grace in Creation and their following in ſtead of it, the Image of Sathan thorow corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>What call you actuall ſinne?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Al the fruits and effects of our ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall vnrighteouſnes whatſoeuer, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be motions to euil in the mind, or conſent or yeelding to ſinne in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding or accompliſhment of the ſame in word or deede.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Why doe you call theſe actuall ſinnes, ſeeing that the moſte of them, ſtande rather in affection then in acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they are indeede, and of their owne nature ſinnes, whatſoeuer pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts ſay to the contrary (who holde that motions to euill, are not euill, if they bee withſtood) as which proceede from that bitter root of originall ſinne, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt indeede be ſinne: Beſides ſith God that is a ſpirit (whoſe pure eis can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not behold wickednes, and who alſo try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the hearts and reynes) being beſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for his vpright iudgement, to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
<pb facs="tcp:28033:32"/> and pronounce touching ſinne, hath in his word ſhut vp euill motions &amp; euill affections, vnder the name of ſinne, they muſt of neceſſitie bee ſo accounted of vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>By how many meanes may ſinne be committed?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Either outwardly, by our words and deedes, as by filthie talking, fooliſhe ſpeech, vncleane actions, &amp;c. Or inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by our corrupted thoughts, and iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie may bee committed alſo, as well tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ignoraunce, negligence, or carleſnes leauing vndon the good duties that God enioyneth vs to doe, as willinglye and willingly performing, the euill thinges that he hath forbidden vs by his law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Let mee heare in fewe wordes what profit you make by all this ſpeech of ſinne?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt I learne, that in as much as Gods lawe is a plaine meane to diſcouer good &amp; euil, I ſhould therefore vſe it as a notable inſtrument, both to confirme me in goodnes, giuing it this priuiledg ouer me, that it ſhould for euer ouer rule al the thoughts of my heart, all the wordes of my mouth, and all the workes of my
<pb facs="tcp:28033:32"/> handes, and alſo to ſtrengthen me againſt all ſinne, both in affection and action, and the rather becauſe God by his word hath condemned the ſame. Secondly, that for as much as a world of ſinne lyeth lurking within my corrupted nature, I ſhoulde learne thereby, not onelye to ſuſpect my ſelfe, and euery thing that I my ſelf like of, as who by corruption, doe loue and like the worſt thinges, but diligently to take heede alſo, that either by the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or ſubtilties of ſinne, which indure but for a while, or thorow the ignorance or parcialitie of mine owne heart, I bee not deceiued. Thirdly that for as much, as ſinne maye bee committed ſo manye wayes, I ſhoulde in all holye care and a good conſcience, bee watchfull ouer my ſelfe, not onelye, that I bee not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken with the acte of ſinne, (a thinge that Hipocrites greatlye regarde) but that the affections of euill preuail not vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon me, abſteining in my heart, what I can, from motions and conſent thereto, and in my outwarde countenaunce, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, wordes, and deeds, from all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of euill.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28033:33"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Ther remaineth one thing, which I had almoſt fogotten, wherof notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtanding I would be glad to hear your minde, &amp; the rather becauſe it is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable point, both for knowledge and comfort, manye of Gods Children in the time of their diſtreſſes, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how to anſwere an aſſault, that ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vppe in them, to wit, whether they haue repented, yea, or no, Tell me ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by what teſtimonies and tokens, may we be aſſured of our repentance, that it is right, ſpeciallye before God?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I ſuppoſe, that for the peace of a good conſcience in this behalfe, we ſhuld looke firſte into our affections, and ſee whether they bee trulie turned from that loue of euill, and hatred of good, whiche was in them, thorow corruption of nature to a ſincere deteſtation of euill, and an vnfeigned deſire and delight in thinges acceptable before God and men, which if in due examination wee finde, they maye then miniſter no doubt ſome comforte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. Secondly, we are to conſider what fruits haue followed this alteration and chaung of our affections, as wel towards
<pb facs="tcp:28033:33"/> God as towardes men, and towards our ſelues particularlie: as for example, if be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God we haue ben humbled in vnfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned confeſſion of our tranſgreſſions, and in earneſt crauing forgiuenes of former ſinnes, and praying for power againſte ſubſequent iniquities, and all this wee haue requeſted for Chriſt Ieſus his ſake: if towardes men, they haue made vs in chriſtian charitie to labor, the ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of them that ſtand, and to pitty and pray for ſuch as be ouertaken, wee doing alſo what we can to pull them out of that filthie puddle of their corruption: and if, as in regarde of our ſelues, they haue brought foorth in vs, feare that wee fall not into the like, deſire care, and indeuor of a better courſe, wrath againſte our ſinnes, and our ſelues for our ſinnes ſake, &amp; the vſing of euery good and holy mean, both outward and inward, for the repreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of all ſinne generally, and ſpeciallye of our particuler iniquities: then I ſaye, I ſee no reaſon, but if wee haue founde theſe and ſuch like fruits, ſoundly ſettled in our heartes (though happely we haue them not in ſo large a portion, and great
<pb facs="tcp:28033:34"/> meaſure as gladly we would) wee ſhould bee thorowlie aſſured of our repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>To ſhutte vp this point of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, and ſo to proceede to the reſt remayning: Tell me why doe you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund repentaunce, rather now, then at other times?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe Chriſt now, is more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and plentifully exhibited vnto be, and ſette as it were before all our ſenſes, our eies, eares, taſtes, and all beeing in ſome ſorte, as it were ſatisfied with him and conueying him after a ſort down into our heartes, to dwell there by fayth, that ſo hee may make vs fruitfull to euery good worke. Both which thinges, that he may the more delightfully do for vs, and in vs, as in reſpect of our ſelues it ſtandeth vs in hande, more mightelye to labour the purging of our ſelues, from all filthines of the fleſhe and the ſpirite, and to haue our ſanctification thorowly perfected in the feare of God, otherwiſe hee will not take pleaſure to dwell or worke in vs, becauſe the LORDE Ieſus cannot abide to haue his aboade, in an vncleane ſoule.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28033:34"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Let vs nowe come to the fourth thing, meete and neceſſarye, for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye religious pertaker at the Lordes table, whiche alſo I deſire of you to know what it is?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Sincere loue towards al men, and euen particulerly towardes our enemies</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>What do you mean by loue heer?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not only the vnfeigned affection, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heart, though y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be the firſt beginning and root of loue, but alſo the ſounde teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of it, by outward ſignes, as coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce, behauiour, words, deedes, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>And why do you exact ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and ſinceritie in this loue.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That ſo wee might, the better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue that diſſembling and hipocriſy both of heart and word, that reſteth in our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature, and willingly giue ouer our ſelues, to yeelde obedience to the rules of the word, which enioyneth vs, to let loue be without diſſimulation, and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs, that we ſhould not loue in word, neither in tongue onely, but in deede and in truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Why do you require ſound loue towardes all men?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28033:35"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe Gods worde in manye places of it, demandeth that duetie of vs: alſo the example of our heauenlye father, towardes all mankinde leadeth vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: and that common creation and bonde of nature, that is amongeſt vs ſhoulde prouoke vs to it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>But muſt wee loue all men alike: and ſhewe the like teſtimonies of loue to all?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I ſuppoſe not ſo, but our loue muſt be ruled, ſpeciallye in the actions, teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiyng it eyther according to the abillitie that God hath indued vs our ſelues with all, yet ſo that we preferre in our wants, the chiefe and moſt principall duties: or elſe according to the worthie graces, that he hath beſtowed vpon his Children, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes notwithſtanding hauing reſpecte vnto the moſt excellent. I will with your good patience, in two or three woordes, make my meaning more playne, that ſo you may perceiue your labour not loſt in the former inſtructions that you haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen mee touching this point. If manye ſtand in neede, either of bodily or ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſuccour, and thorow want of ability or
<pb facs="tcp:28033:35"/> otherwiſe, I am not able to releeue them all, then my minde is, that thoſe are moſt to be preferred, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I am moſt ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bound, either by the bond of nature, or chriſtian profeſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>What reaſons haue you to leade you to this?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, the plain words of the text, which as it chargeth vs to doe good vnto all, ſo will it haue vs eſpecially to regard the houſhold of faith. Secondly, we haue the examples, as of many good men, ſo of one that is greater then all exception, Chriſte Ieſus himſelfe, who though he loued all his Diſciples, yet adorned one aboue the reſt, with this title, <hi>The diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple whom Ieſus loued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>But this ſhould ſeeme to approue of reſpect of perſons, &amp; to be a mean of great emulation &amp; contentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amongſt the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of the body of the church?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not ſo neither, becauſe here is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of man eſteemed, but onely Gods graces, according as he hath made vs to ſee them in our ſelues or others, rightlie reuerenced, which alſo ſhalbe ſo farre of, from breeding iarres or diſlikes, that it
<pb facs="tcp:28033:36"/> ſhalbe a notable ſpurre to all goodnes, in as much as they that be indued with the beſt partes, ſhalbe moſt loued and beſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked; from which likewiſe ther ſhall flowe a third commodity, namely, that our loue, which is now carried away with wordly reſpectes, and carnal conſiderations, ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be ouerruled as it were, and moſt ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie reſtrained to ſpirituall and heauenlie bleſſinges?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why do you adde particulerlie, towardes our enemies?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The more deeply to ſound our own loue: for wee loue them that loue vs what greate thing do wee, and the better to trie our obedience to god, who requireth this greate duetie at our handes: in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance wherof alſo, we our ſelues (ſone be ſoundlie done) maie reape ſinguler com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte, in as much, firſte as wee ſee Gods ſpirite, &amp; power fully working in vs, the practiſe of that, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which thorow the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of our nature wee are moſt farre. Secondly becauſe it is an vndoubted te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of our ſound affection to Gods Saints, in as much as we loue them that euen for well doyng, do hate and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute
<pb facs="tcp:28033:36"/> both vs and them, wee hoping yet further her alſo, that God in ſuch ſort will ſo bleſſe our pore obedience in this behalfe, performed according to his word, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other men by our example, ſhall in ſome ſorte be drawen on, to do like towardes vs and others alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. <hi>But this is a harde, yea an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible thinge for vs, as in reſpecte of our ſeluese ſpecially, to accompliſhe and performe?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi> I confeſſe that to bee true, howbeit the more neede wee haue for that, to ſtriue to the dooing of it, not making the difficultie of this duetie, a meane to diſcourage vs, as manye doe in this and manye other poyntes, but to encourage vs rather, knowing that this beeing once perfourmed by the power of Gods ſpirite that dwelleth in vs, GOD by this ſhall reape more glorye, as whoſe power ſhall the more plainely appeare, by how much the worke was hard, and altogeather impoſſible as in reſpecte of vs: and wee oure ſelues ſhall receiue more comfort, in that weake fleſhe and bloude hath bene inabled
<pb facs="tcp:28033:37"/> by him vnfaynedly to doe that, from the leaſt thought whereof, we were moſt far remooued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>What reaſons haue you to lead you to the doing of this, ſo harde and excellent a dutie?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Firſt, manye commaundementes contayned in the word, and namely, <hi>Mat. <hi>5.</hi> Luk <hi>6.27.</hi>
               </hi> where we are expreſly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to loue our enemies, &amp;c. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Gods owne practize, who loued vs when we were his enemies, and yet te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth his loue towards all, making his ſunne to ſhine, and his raine to fall vpon the iuſt and vniuſt. Thirdly, Chriſts own example who loued, and as a ſigne of his loue, prayed for them that put him to death, as the Euangeliſte recordeth. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which, if eyther thorow Sathans ſubtlety, or in our owne ignoraunce, wee will ſay, that Chriſt did this as God: we are fourthly to regarde the example of manie of Gods ſayntes, and particulerly of <hi>Steuen,</hi> who as appeareth, <hi>Act. <hi>7.60.</hi>
               </hi> compaſſed about with fleſh and blood like vnto our ſelues, did the like, in perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our owne heartes, that God which
<pb facs="tcp:28033:37"/> performed it in him and others, will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh the ſame in vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>What fruit and comfort ſhal you reape by this ſincere loue in you, and the effects thereof?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Great and many doutleſſe: as firſt it is a plaine badge and cogniſance, both to my ſelf and others, that I am Chriſts diſciple. Secondly, it is one aſſured argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that I am tranſlated out of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes into light. Thirdly, it ſealeth vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me this, that I am a ſound and feeling member of the bodie of Chriſt. Fourthly, it certifieth my conſcience, that the ſaints and ſeruants of God doe vnfainedly loue me. And laſtly, it is a certain pledge, that I am in ſome meaſure fit for praier, with out the which alſo, euen all the ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the faythfull, ſhalbe abominable in Gods ſight, hurtfull to their owne ſoules, and vnprofitable to others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>And why doe you require loue now, more then at all other times, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is a duty that we ſhould walk in, all the daies and times of our liues?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Becauſe wee receiue now, a more excellent pledge of that holye loue,
<pb facs="tcp:28033:38"/> that is and ought to be, betwixt the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſts body, then at other times. And therefore good reaſon, that in ſound loue wee ſhould be more fitte, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of that which God giueth vs, not onely to expreſſe our mutuall loue by, but there beeing alſo a certaine proportion and good agreement, betweene the thing offered and receiued, we might more and more be ſtrengthened, and made to grow vp therein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Which is the laſt thing of al, requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to this holy action of the Supper?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Humble thankeſgiuing to almigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie God for all his mercies, and namlye, for thoſe that he offereth vs, at that hys holy table: which though it come in the laſt place, yet is it not of the leaſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, as by whiche, becauſe it is the principall part of this action, the whole action it ſelfe is many times named: and being rightly performed, is a good mean doutles, to haue that and al other mercies continued vpon vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Why doe you require humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in your thankeſgiuing?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, to beat downe the pride of
<pb facs="tcp:28033:38"/> our own conceits, who are then ſpeciallie puffed vp, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue receiued moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces from god: alſo becauſe we are aſſured, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> without it, whatſoeuer ſeruice we offer vp to God, and therefore our thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing likewiſe ſhalbe abhominable in his ſight, for as it is true that God on the one ſide, reſiſteth the proud euen vnto their faces, generallye in all their facts, &amp; moſt ſpecially in ſuche ſeruices as they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to performe to him: ſo doth hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in, and giue grace to the lowly and meek, ſpecially to ſuch, as be ſo caſt down in themſelues, that they feel, that not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their owne ſinnes, haue made a fearful ſeperation betwixt God and them (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it pleaſe him, in Chriſts innocency and righteouſneſſe to cure and couer the ſame) but alſo that the workes of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, which God hath inabled them to performe, are (not as they come from him or of themſelues, but alſo as they taſt of the remainders of our corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) as filthy &amp; ſtained clouts in his ſight, if they ſhuld be tried by his moſt exact iudgement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>And what is this thankeſgiuing you ſpeake of and require?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28033:39"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not onely a gratefull receiuing of Gods benefites, as in regard of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of our minde, though that indeed bee the principall, and which God moſt reſpecteth, and wee our ſelues may reape moſt comfort by: neither yet a ſanctified vſe of them, which alſo is ſome teſtimony both of our reuerence and thankefulneſſe towards him that giueth the ſame, and of faith in our ſelues, but alſo an vnfeigned declaration (which I adde the better to ſhutte out hipocriſie) of our thankefull hearts, firſt by the words of our mouthes continuallie ſpeaking vnto his prayſes, that hath delt ſo liberallye and largelye with vs miſerable wretches, not worthy of the leaſt benefit of this life, much leſſe of that whiche is to come: and ſecondly, by the deedes of a holie conuerſation, in ſome meaſure aunſwerable to thoſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and a notable meane alſo to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the care and kindneſſe of our hearts, towardes God in his graces moſt plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully powred forth vpon vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Why ſay you to almightie God? may we not yeeld thanks to men alſo?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> I name him becauſe hee is the
<pb facs="tcp:28033:39"/> onely founteine, from whence alone flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all godnes to vs ward, and therefore indeede to him alone belongeth all praiſe and thankeſgiuing for the ſame. Not minding yet hereby to debarre men from thanking one an other, in the gyftes that they communicate one to an other: for piety or performance of duty to God, doth not deſtroy humanitie or courteous dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling one towards an other. And yet herin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> men muſt be alwaies circumſpect, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they rob not God of his glory, in the whole, or in any part of it, which they ſhal do, if they make or take men to bee anye more then inſtruments or meanes of Gods mercie towardes them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>That that followeth, me thinketh ſeemeth impoſſible for vs to performe, namelye, that wee ſhoulde yeelde God thanks for all his mercies, ſith they are infinit and innumerable. The conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration wherof, alſo ſhuld greatly caſt vs down, ſith we faile in a duty of ſo great a moment and waight. Tell me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what is that you meane thereby?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I deny not but confeſſe, that Gods mercies are as you ſay infinit &amp; inumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,
<pb facs="tcp:28033:40"/> &amp; that it is indeed impoſſible for vs to account them all; muche more impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible worthelye to praiſe him for them or any one of them. But as in vnfeined con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of our own infinite tranſgreſſions before him, we haue ſome peece of a good conſcience, in the general laying of them out, and in a particuler rentall of ſo many of them as we can call to memorie: ſo no doubt in this action, this may comfort vs that though we cannot call to mind, euery one of his mercies particularlye, yet wee ceaſe not in general termes, to praiſe him for all, and particulerly to recount as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye as wee can? that ſo both waies, our thankefulnes may be both earneſt &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall: we dealing further in this, as in all other good duties, namely in forceing our ſelues to the vttermoſte of graces re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, to the careful performance of this holy ſeruice, cleauing yet when we haue done, for the couering and curing of our wants heer, as in all other works of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes and fruites of our faith, to the fulnes of perfection and holines in our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, who is therefore giuen vnto vs, not onely to take away ſinne, but to ſupply al
<pb facs="tcp:28033:40"/> our defects, that ſo euery manner of way, he might become wholy ours for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>How many ſortes of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are there towardes vs?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Two in my iudgement, euen as wee our ſelues, conſiſt of two partes, to wit, the one, outward as our bodies, and the other, inward as our ſoules, and as we know &amp; beleeue, that there are two liues, the one temporall heere, and the other e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall in the world to come. Of the firſt ſort, are peace, plentie, health, godly Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats, good lawes, &amp; ſundrie ſuche like, for whiche we are bound dailye to praiſe God, becauſe we daily inioy the ſame. Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond ſort, are fayth, repentance, forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenes of our ſinnes, and all good meanes wherby theſe things are begun begotten &amp; continued in vs: which becauſe they are ſpiritual, do no doubt more neceſſarily be long, to the good eſtate of our ſoules, then the former to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſeruation of our bodies Theſe latter beeing again of two ſortes: ſome reſpecting this life preſent, as the Miniſterye of Gods woorde, cellebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Sacramentes, execution of Chryſtes Diſciplyne, earneſt prayers,
<pb facs="tcp:28033:41"/> and Gods holy ſpirite, by the powerfull working wherof, all theſe are made fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: oth or ſome concerning the life that is to come, as the ſaluaion of our ſoules, in the day of Chriſt, the comfortable fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of Gods preſence for euermore, &amp;c. The former notwithſtandinge beeing means to bring vs to the poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſe latter, and therefore good reaſon, why we ſhould reuerently receiue them, and rightly vſe them to thoſe ends and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes whereunto God him ſelfe hath bene pleaſed, in great mercy to vs ward to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>But ought we to be alike thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to God for all his mercies?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> True it is, that we ſhould let none of them ſlip out of our memories, nor bee vnthankfull for the leaſt, if wee could tell how, becauſe the leaſt of them exceedeth all the thankes that we are able to yeeld: Howbeit thoſe that are moſte excellent, ſhould fetch from vs moſt humble &amp; harty thanks, otherwiſe we ſhall depriue God of a principal part of his glory, whilſt we giue him ſmalleſt thanks, for his greateſt benefits, &amp; bewray ſlender iudgement in
<pb facs="tcp:28033:41"/> our ſelues, that are not able to diſcern be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the beſt and the meaneſt of Gods mercies, yea, we ſhall ſpoile our ſelues of that hope, that wee might haue of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance and increaſe of his goodnes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs, becauſe the more dutifullye thankfull wee are towards him (that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo being his owne grace wrought in vs) the more hope wee haue ſtill to receiue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>You ſayd, wee ſhould eſpeciallye thanke him for the graces, that hee is pleaſed to beſtow vppon vs, at that his holy table: But why ſay you ſo?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> As well becauſe we haue then, a ſpeciall prouocation giuen vs thereto, in the right vſe of the Supper, thoſe graces beeing after a ſort plainelye propounded vnto all our ſenſes, as alſo becauſe that the graces that are there offered, bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſpeciall and ſinguler merrites, if we conſider, either our vnworthines that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them, (miſerable men that we are) or the great goodnes of God the grace of them, or the excelency of the graces them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that be offered to vs therein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt. <hi>What are thoſe graces I pray you?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28033:42"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Many and diuers, yea infinite and innumerable, ſpeciallie Chriſtes deathe, and the moſt comfortable fruites and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, that flow from the ſame, to al faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full communicants, becauſe in them, hys death, and the fruites following it, connot bee ſundered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>What is there in the ſupper, that may lead vs to Chriſtes death, or maye put vs as it were in poſſeſſion of it and the fruits of the ſame?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The breaking of the breade, and the powring forth of the wine, doe moſte liuely ſet before the eies of my faith, the crucifiyng of Chriſtes body, and the ſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his bloud, though that were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed many hundred yeares agoe, this being one ſpeciall propertie of faith, (as hath bene ſaide already) to make things paſt preſent; And I am made pertaker of the ſame, with all graces flowing from it, in as much as according to Chriſts or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce and commandement, I take the breade and eat it, and drincke likewiſe of that miſticall cuppe, by faith, aſſuring my ſelfe, that as verelie as that bread is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and that Wine powred forth before
<pb facs="tcp:28033:42"/> mine eies, ſo verely was Chriſtes bodye crucified, and his bloud ſhedde vppon the Croſſe for me, to the forgiuenes of all my ſinnes. And as verely as I eat the bread and drinke the wine, hoping that it ſhall turne to the nouriſhment of my outward man, and comforte of my heart, ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely Chriſt and his merites, are and ſhall be the ſpirituall food and ioy of my ſoule, euen to eternal ſaluation and euerlaſting life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>What bee the principall fruites flowing from Chriſts death vnto vs?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> We haue by Chriſtes death, theſe eſpeciallye: firſte, the forgiueneſſe of all oure ſinnes, the Scripture bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring recorde to this trueth, and ſaying: Chriſte died for our ſinnes, and agayne, the bloud of Chriſte doth purge vs from all our iniquities. Secondlie, we haue ſtrength againſt the power of ſinne, the Apoſtle telling vs in the ſpirit of truth that our old man crucified is with him, that the bodye of Sinne might bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed. Thirdlye, Sinne beeing ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken awaye by his death, the curſſe that lay vppon the Creatures for it, is
<pb facs="tcp:28033:43"/> alſo remoued, and we in the taking away thereof, haue the ſame ſanctified to our lawfull vſes. Fourthly by his death, we haue not onely the rage of naturall death aſſwaged, but are thereby deliuered from eternall death, hauing by meanes of his obedience alſo, a ready way, and ſpeedie paſſage to eternall life, which alſo is and ought to bee taken, euen for a moſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall fruite of his death and ſufferinges. For had our ſauior by his death, brought vnto vs the former graces onely, and yet appointed vs to haue liued heer in mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde calamities, and perſecutions vnder the wicked, or ſuffered our ſoules to ſleep as ſome dreame and ſuppoſe, we had ben moſt miſerable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>I reioyce greatly, in the reaſons that you haue hetherto ſoundlye ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, touching your faith, and hope, wiſhing you more and more to inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour the increaſe of all feeling, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and holy obedience in theſe and all other thinges that maye concerne Gods glory, the good of his children &amp; your owne comfort, both in this life, and that that is to come. But tell mee
<pb facs="tcp:28033:43"/> plainly, haue you a minde and deſire to ſtriue thereto?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Yea, I thanke God for it in ſome meaſure: and I beſeech him harte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to continue, with increaſe of the ſame in me for euer: And I pray you in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, let me be aſſiſted with your earneſt prayers, both publike and priuate, as I haue bene heretofore.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>And purpoſe you at all times, to meditate of theſe good things ſpoken, but ſpeciallye then, when you ſit at the Lords table, with the reſt of the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Yea the Lord ſtrengthening me thereto, and inabling mee by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, to maiſter mine own corruption and to ſubdue the ſtraggling thoughts of my heart and head.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Though vpon this that you haue confeſſed, I am willing to admitte you, to the participation of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, yet let me I pray you, ſound you a little further, in ſome neceſſary points, for me and you before wee drawe to an end. Do you for the time repent from the bottome of your hart, and wil you
<pb facs="tcp:28033:44"/> vnfeignedlie in time to come heereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, alwaies deteſte all corrupt, erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and hereticall opinions, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulerlye that of poperye, which is a monſtrous body, bombazed &amp; patch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, of all hereſies that euer haue bene?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Yea with all my heart, and will moſt willingly performe, that which you require, by the grace of GOD, without whome I cannot do any thing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>And wil you not ſuffer your ſelfe thorow ſeducing ſpirites, that are ſent abroade into the worlde, by Antychriſt that man of ſin, to peruert mens ſoules to haue your affection in any part with drawen from dutifull obedience, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our gracious ſoueraigne, Queene Elizabeth, her inferior Mgiſtrates, and Godly lawes? Or if God ſhould ſende as a iuſt puniſhment vppon vs for our ſinnes, alteration and chaunge in our ſtate and religion, will you not reuolt and fal away from the truth, now pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likelye preached and profeſſed in oure land?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No the Lord aſſiſting me. As for her maieſty I wilbe alwayes ready, with
<pb facs="tcp:28033:44"/> goodes, lands, life, and all that I haue, to yelde obedience vnto her in the lord, and for the Lord, and touching religion now preſentlie eſtabliſhed, I purpoſe thorowe Gods goodnes, whatſoeuer ſhall fall out, to liue and die therein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. <hi>Now the very God of peace that brought againe from the dead, oure Lord Ieſus, the great ſhepheard of the ſheep, thorow the bloud of the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting couenaunt, ſanctifie you thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, that your whole ſpirite, and ſoule, and body, may be kept blameleſſe vnto the comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and make you continually perfect in al good workes, alwaies to do his will, he working in you that which is pleſaunt in his ſight, thorow Ieſus Chriſt, who together with the father, and the holie ghoſt, three perſons and one eternall God, be magnified and prayſed of vs: and of all people, both now and at all times, for euer and euer?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> So bee it (good Lorde) euen ſo bee it.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
